A Guide to the Personal Papers of Mary A. Marshall, 1938-1992
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Personal Papers of Mary A. Marshall, 1938-1992
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
RG 65
20 boxes.
Marshall, Mary A. R. (Mary Aydelotte Rice), 1921-1992
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Roger D. Marshall in 1994.
Biographical Information
Born Mary Rice in 1921, Mary A. Marshall graduated from Swarthmore College and came to Washington, DC, in 1942 to work as an economist in the Department of Justice. In 1944 she married Roger D. Marshall and they moved to Arlington in 1953. Prominent in Arlington County politics in the 1950s and early 1960s, Marshall first served at chair of the Arlington County Democratic Committee in 1961, acting as the new liberal wing of the party in the face of the Byrd Machine and Massive Resistance to school desegregation. Marshall was elected in 1965 as a Democrat to represent Arlington in the Virginia House of Delegates, taking the seat of the retiring Kathryn Stone, another "housewife" turned state representative.
In the General Assembly, Marshall chaired the Counties, Cities, and Towns Committee and served on the Privileges and Elections Committee, the Committee on Health Institutions and Welfare, and the Roads and Internal Navigation Committee. She was a co-founder of the Women's Round Table, a network of legislators and organizations interested in women's issues. She showed special interest in legislation concerning the elderly and served on the Federal Council on Aging from 1978 to 1981. Marshall introduced legislation protecting the rights of the mentally ill and establishing the first state-wide child care licensing law. As a member of the Virginia Library Board, she promoted an increase in state aid for libraries. Marshall represented Arlington in the House of Delegates from 1966 to 1970, lost reelection, and then returned to Richmond from 1972 to 1992. After retiring from politics, Marshall died after a fall in October that same year.
Scope and Content
The personal papers described in this guide were chiefly generated or collected by Mary A. Marshall in the course of her political career in the Virginia House of Delegates. The collection measures nine linear feet and contains material dating from 1938 to 1992, with the bulk from her last twenty years in the General Assembly, 1971-1991. Types of material include legislative subject files, legislative bills, press releases, campaign literature and correspondence, engagement calendars, photographs, and clippings.
Marshall's subject files (Series 1, Alphabetical Files) and collection of bills she sponsored (Series 2, Legislation) document her efforts to improve life for the elderly, develop public libraries, and her interest in high quality public education and equity for women. Series 1 contains folders on her areas of concern, yearly programs, and supplementary material from the Women's Round Table. This series also has a collection of bumper stickers representing local, state, and national political races and championing particular issues. Series 2 starts with general legislation passed, then moves into specific bills Marshall sponsored or co-authored. Series 4, Campaign Literature, contains campaign literature for both for Marshall and others, representing national, state, and local races, and Republican, Democratic, and independent candidates, questionnaires from local groups, correspondence, issue statements, financial reports on campaign donations, and expenditures. Series 8, Photographs, has individual images of Marshall in Files 2 through 7; Files 8 through 15 have Marshall with other featured people. File 16 has partial and complete contact sheets of portraits and staged group photos, and File 17 has photos that do not show Marshall, although there is a portrait of her husband Roger. Series 8, Planners, contains Marshall's daily planners and calendars, purchased or received from the League of Women Voters, Swarthmore College, and the Metropolitan Museum of Art, which has handwritten appointments and notes throughout each one. She listed out personal, legislative, and political activities and appointments.
Arrangement
Record Group 65 is arranged into eight series by type of material. Series 1 is filed alphabetically by folder title/subject matter, and the series on legislation, news clippings, and political campaigns are arranged chronologically. Series 8, Planners, are housed in oversized and clamshell boxes but are still listed and shelved with the rest of the collection. Folders containing photographs have an asterisk [*] after the file name. Folders with oversized materials and artifacts have a double asterisk [**] to denote where material was removed and separation sheets added.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
RG 26, Campaign Literature, has campaign flyers for Marshall for several election cycles. Marshall was very active in the community; collections for groups where she was a member are RG 33, Records of the American Association of University Women, Arlington Branch, RG 97, Records of Church Women United, and RG 123, Records of Rock Spring Congregational United Church of Christ. Mary Margaret Whipple, another Arlington representative in Richmond, has materials in RG 168, Personal Papers of Mary Margaret Whipple.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Arlington County (Va.) -- Politics and government.; Political parties -- United States.; Virginia -- Politics and government.; Voting -- United States.; Women -- United States.; Marshall, Mary A. R. (Mary Aydelotte Rice Marshall), 1921-1992; Arlington (Va.); Arlington County (Va.)
Contents List
- Alphabetical Files
  - Aging: Center for Gerontology (Box 1)
  - Aging: Commission on the Needs of Elderly Virginians, 1973-1978 (Box 1)
  - Aging: Federal Aging Reports, 1978-1981 (Box 1)
  - Aging: Federal Council on Aging: Appointment Papers, 1978-1981 (Box 1)
  - Aging: Federal Council on Aging, correspondence, 1975-1981 (Box 1)
  - Aging: "Programs Serving the Elderly in Sweden and Denmark" (Box 1)
  - Aging: Miscellaneous Reports, 1974-1989 (Box 1)
  - American Association of University Women, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Arlington Democratic Committee: member lists, Chairman Reports, By-Laws, 1961-1991 (Box 1)
  - Articles & Speeches by Mary Marshall, 1976-1991 (1) (Box 1)
  - Articles & Speeches by Mary Marshall, 1976-1991 (2) (Box 1)
  - Articles & Speeches by Mary Marshall, 1976-1991 (3) (Box 1)
  - Awards, 1982-1991 (Box 1)
  - Raffle Winner Marshall, the "Fishnet", September 1981 (Box 1)
  - Ballot Design: Correspondence, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Biographies of Mary Marshall: Archival, n.d., 1968-1991 (Box 1)
  - Biographies of Mary Marshall, 1961-1991 (Box 1)
  - Bumper Stickers** (Box 2)
  - Byrd Machine in Virginia, 1965-1975 (Box 2)
  - Calendar, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Cannon Control, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - "Capitol Connections", 1992 (Box 2)
  - Child Care Reports, 1986-1992 ** (Box 2)
  - Child Care: State Democrats, 1988, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Child Care: State Democrats, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Child Support, 1985-1990 (Box 2)
  - Child Support Report, "Development of Guidelines for Child Support Orders", 1987 (Box 2)
  - Charles Colson Correspondence, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Congratulations (Letters), 1963-1969 (Box 2)
  - Congratulations (Letters), 1970-1979 (Box 2)
  - Congratulations (Letters), 1980-1989 (Box 2)
  - Congratulations (Letters), 1990-1992 ** (Box 3)
  - Constituent Correspondence, 1991 (Box 3)
  - Constitution, Virginia, Revision, Correspondence, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Constitution, Virginia, Revision, House Speeches, Notes, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Constitution, Virginia, Revision, House Votes, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Constitution, Virginia, Revision, Legislative Publications, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Constitution, Virginia, Revision, Marshall Newsletters, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Constitution, Virginia, Revision, Newspaper Clippings, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Constitution, Virginia, Revision, Organization & Individual Positions, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Consumer Council, Virginia Citizen, 1991 (Box 3)
  - Dulles Toll Road Correspondence, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Earned Income Tax Credit, 1988-1992 (Box 3)
  - Education: Summary & Final Reports, 1991 (Box 3)
  - Education in Arlington, 1987 - July 1991 (Box 3)
  - Education in Arlington, August - November 1991 (Box 3)
  - Education in Arlington, December 1991 - 1992 (Box 3)
  - Election Law: Reapportionment, 1989 (Box 4)
  - Election Law: Reapportionment, 1990 (Box 4)
  - Election Law: Reapportionment, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Election Returns, 1965-1985 ** (Box 4)
  - Expense Account Forms (Box 4)
  - Health: Brochures on Diet (Box 4)
  - Health Care Coalition, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Health Legislation, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Health: Long-Term Care, 1978-1989 (Box 4)
  - Health: "Long-Term Care of the Elderly," 1987 (Box 4)
  - Health Professions Board, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Health: Mary Marshall Speech, 1981 (Box 4)
  - Humor: Clippings, 1989-1992 (Box 4)
  - Hunger Foundation, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Joint Custody, 1986 (Box 4)
  - Judges: Correspondence, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Kaiser Permanente Publications, 1991-1992 (Box 4)
  - Legislation Patron Reports, 1975-1981 (Box 4)
  - Legislation Patron Reports, 1982-1990 (Box 4)
  - Library: Arlington County, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Charles McDowell Columns, 1981 (Box 5)
  - William McGuffey's Ash, 1976-1991 (Box 5)
  - Medical Society of Virginia Foundation, 1991-1992 (Box 5)
  - Mentally Ill and Retarded: Correspondence, 1985 (Box 5)
  - Mentally Ill and Retarded: Reports, 1966-1972 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous Articles (Box 5)
  - National Council of State Legislatures; Statement of Mary Marshall, 1981 (Box 5)
  - National Conference of State Legislatures Trip, 1987-1988 (Box 5)
  - Newsletters from Mary Marshall, 1969-1990 (Box 5)
  - Office Assignment: Correspondence, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Office Equipment Literature (Box 5)
  - "Procrustes" Articles, 1987-1990 (Box 5)
  - "Procrustes Award" Mailing, 1989-1990 (Box 5)
  - "Procrustes" Clippings, 1989-1990 (Box 5)
  - "Procrustes" Correspondence, 1989-1991 (Box 5)
  - "Procrustes" Report, 1990-1991 (Box 5)
  - Ratings/Polls, 1974-1987 (1) (Box 5)
  - Ratings/Polls, 1974-1987 (2) (Box 5)
  - Redistricting, 1989 (Box 5)
  - United Seniors Health Cooperative, 1992 (Box 5)
  - Uranium, Clipping, 1984 (Box 5)
  - Women Attorneys Association Foundation, 1987-1993 (Box 5)
  - Women: Clippings, 1979-1987 (Box 5)
  - Women: General: Brochures, 1983-1984 (Box 6)
  - Women's Health Conference, 1985 (Box 6)
  - Women's Round Table, 1979 (Box 6)
  - Women's Round Table, 1980 (Box 6)
  - Women's Round Table, 1981 (Box 6)
  - Women's Round Table, 1982 (Box 6)
  - Women's Round Table, 1983 (Box 6)
  - Women's Round Table, 1984 (Box 6)
  - Women's Round Table, 1985 (Box 6)
  - Women's Round Table, 1986 (Box 6)
  - Women's Round Table, 1987 (Box 6)
  - Women's Round Table, 1988 (Box 6)
  - Women's Round Table, 1989 (Box 6)
  - Women's Round Table, 1990 (Box 6)
  - Women's Round Table, 1991 (Box 6)
- Legislation
  - Summaries of Legislation, 1968-1975 (Box 6)
  - Summaries of Legislation, 1976 (Box 6)
  - Summaries of Legislation, 1977 (Box 6)
  - Summaries of Legislation, 1978 ** (Box 6)
  - Digest of Legislation, 1979 (Box 6)
  - Summaries of Legislation, 1979 (Box 7)
  - Mary Marshall Bills, 1978 (Box 7)
  - Mary Marshall Bills, 1979 (Box 7)
  - Mary Marshall Bills, 1980 (Box 7)
  - Mary Marshall Bills, 1981 (Box 7)
  - Mary Marshall Bills, January 1982 (Box 7)
  - Mary Marshall Bills, February 1982 (Box 7)
  - Mary Marshall Bills, January 12-21, 1983 (Box 7)
  - Mary Marshall Bills, January 24, 1983 (Box 7)
  - Mary Marshall Bills, February 1983 (Box 7)
  - Mary Marshall Bills, January 1984 (Box 7)
  - Mary Marshall Bills, February 1984 (Box 7)
  - Mary Marshall Bills, January 1-14, 1986 (Box 7)
  - Mary Marshall Bills, January 15, 1986 (Box 8)
  - Mary Marshall Bills, January 16-20, 1986 (Box 8)
  - Mary Marshall Bills, January 21-31, 1986 (Box 8)
  - Mary Marshall Bills, February - March 1986 (Box 8)
  - Mary Marshall Bills, 1989-1990 (Box 8)
- Press Releases
  - Mary Marshall Press Releases, 1965 (Box 8)
  - Mary Marshall Press Releases, 1966 (Box 8)
  - Mary Marshall Press Releases, 1967 (Box 8)
  - Mary Marshall Press Releases, 1968 (Box 8)
  - Mary Marshall Press Releases, 1969 (Box 8)
  - Mary Marshall Press Releases, 1970 (Box 8)
  - Mary Marshall Press Releases, 1971 (Box 8)
  - Mary Marshall Press Releases, 1972 (Box 8)
  - Mary Marshall Press Releases, 1973 (Box 8)
  - Mary Marshall Press Releases, 1974 (Box 8)
  - Mary Marshall Press Releases, 1975 (Box 8)
  - Mary Marshall Press Releases, 1976 (Box 8)
  - Mary Marshall Press Releases, 1977 (Box 8)
  - Mary Marshall Press Releases, 1978 (Box 8)
  - Mary Marshall Press Releases, 1979 (Box 8)
- Campaign Papers
  - Campaign: Literature, 1965 (Box 8)
  - Campaign: Literature, 1967 (Box 8)
  - 1969 Campaign: Position Papers, Summaries, 1969 (Box 9)
  - 1969 Campaign: Literature, 1969 ** (Box 9)
  - 1969 Campaign: Correspondence, 1969 (Box 9)
  - 1971 Campaign: Literature, 1971 ** (Box 9)
  - 1971 Campaign: Correspondence, 1971 (Box 9)
  - 1971 Campaign: Position Papers, 1971 (Box 9)
  - 1973 Campaign: Reports, 1973-1974 (Box 9)
  - 1973 Campaign: Literature, 1973 ** (Box 9)
  - 1975 Campaign: Reports, 1974-1975 (Box 9)
  - 1975 Campaign: Literature, 1975 (Box 9)
  - 1976 Campaign: Literature, 1976 ** (Box 9)
  - 1976 Campaign: Correspondence, 1976 (Box 9)
  - 1976 Campaign: Correspondence on Carter Campaign, 1976 (Box 9)
  - 1976 Campaign: Reports, 1976 (Box 9)
  - 1977 Campaign: Literature, 1977 (Box 9)
  - 1977 Campaign: Correspondence, 1977 (Box 9)
  - 1977 Campaign: Reports, 1977 (Box 9)
  - 1978 Campaign: Literature, 1978 (Box 9)
  - 1978 Campaign: Correspondence, 1978 (Box 9)
  - 1979 Campaign: Literature, 1979 (Box 10)
  - 1979 Campaign: Correspondence, 1979 (Box 10)
  - 1979 Campaign: Reports, 1979-1980 (Box 10)
  - 1981 Campaign: Literature, 1981 (Box 10)
  - 1981 Campaign: Reports, 1981-1982 (Box 10)
  - 1982 Campaign: Literature, 1982 ** (Box 10)
  - 1982 Campaign: Correspondence, 1982 (Box 10)
  - 1982 Campaign: Reports, 1982 (Box 10)
  - 1983 Campaign: Literature, 1983 (Box 10)
  - 1983 Campaign: Bonnie Newlon Campaign, 1983 ** (Box 10)
  - 1983 Campaign: Correspondence, 1983 (Box 10)
  - 1983 Campaign: Reports, 1983-1984 (Box 10)
  - 1984 Campaign: Literature, 1984 ** (Box 10)
  - 1985 Campaign: Correspondence, 1983-1985 (Box 10)
  - 1985 Campaign: Reports, 1985-1986 (Box 10)
  - 1985 Campaign: Literature, 1984-1985 (Box 10)
  - 1986 Campaign: Literature, 1986 (Box 11)
  - 1987 Campaign: Literature, 1987 (Box 11)
  - 1987 Campaign: Reports, 1987-1988 ** (Box 11)
  - 1988 Campaign: Literature, 1987-1988 (Box 11)
  - 1988 Campaign: Correspondence, 1987-1988 (Box 11)
  - 1989 Campaign: Literature, 1989 (Box 11)
  - 1991 Campaign: Reports, 1991-1992 (Box 11)
  - 1991 Campaign: Literature, 1991 (Box 11)
  - 1991 Campaign: Correspondence, 1990-1991 (Box 11)
  - 1992 Campaign: Literature, 1992 (Box 11)
- Personal Papers
  - Commission on Incorporation Certificate for Mary Marshall, 1958 (Box 11)
  - Mary Marshall Note Cards for Speech, n.d. (Box 11)
  - Virginia House of Delegates Stationery for Mary Marshall (Box 11)
  - First Day Covers [Commemorative Envelopes], 1973-1976 (Box 11)
  - Edgewood School Diploma for Mary Marshall, 1938 (Box 11)
  - Swarthmore College and Union College Programs, 1942, 1962, 1991 (Box 11)
  - Democratic Convention Memorabilia, 1964, 1968, 1971 (Box 11)
  - U.S. Inaugural Programs and Photographs, 1961-1977 * (Box 11)
  - Virginia Gubernatorial Inauguration Programs and Invitations, 1960-1990 (Box 11)
  - Letters to Mary Marshall from Virginia and Federal Officials, 1969-1989 (Box 11)
  - Cards from Virginia and Federal Officials, 1977-1988 (Box 11)
  - Cards from Nell Marshall, 1972-1988 (Box 12)
  - Washington Post Supplement, July 4, 1976 (Box 12)
  - Metro Opening Ceremonies, Rosslyn Park Ceremonies, 1976, 1989 (Box 12)
  - R.F.P., Virginia Universities Graduate Site, 1992 (Box 12)
  - Parochial Schools, State Aid to, Form Letter (Box 12)
- Photographs
  - Photograph for Campaign Literature, 1965 (Box 12)
  - Mary Marshall Formal Portraits, n.d.* (Box 12)
  - Mary Marshall Close-ups on State House Floor, 1980, 1982, n.d.* (Box 12)
  - Mary Marshall Speaking on State House Floor, 1968-1991, n.d.* (Box 12)
  - Mary Marshall at Desk on State House Floor, 1972-1977, 1983, 1985, n.d.* (Box 12)
  - Mary Marshall Speaking Engagements and Other Work, 1971-1991, n.d.* (Box 12)
  - Mary Marshall Trips, 1978, 1980 * (Box 12)
  - Staged Group Photographs, 1962-1984, n.d. (1)* (Box 12)
  - Staged Group Photographs, 1962-1984, n.d. (2)* (Box 12)
  - Informal Group and Reception Photographs, 1964-1984, n.d.* (Box 13)
  - Informal Groupings on State House Floor, 1968-1988, n.d. (1)* (Box 13)
  - Informal Groupings on State House Floor, 1968-1988, n.d. (2)* (Box 13)
  - Groupings at Speaking Engagements and Committees, 1966-1982, n.d.* (Box 13)
  - Constituent Work, 1966-1989, n.d.* (Box 13)
  - Family Groups, Friend Groups, Trips, 1978-1982, n.d.* (Box 13)
  - Contact Sheets, 1975, 1978, n.d.* (Box 13)
  - Not Featuring Mary Marshall, 1978, n.d.* (Box 13)
- Clippings
  - 1958-1973 (Box 13)
  - 1974 (Box 13)
  - 1975 (Box 13)
  - 1976 (Box 13)
  - 1977 (Box 13)
  - 1978 (Box 14)
  - 1979 (Box 14)
  - 1980 (Box 14)
  - 1981 (Box 14)
  - 1982 (Box 14)
  - 1983 (Box 14)
  - 1984 (Box 14)
  - 1985 (Box 14)
  - 1986 (Box 14)
  - 1987 (Box 15)
  - 1988 (Box 15)
  - 1989 ** (Box 15)
  - 1990 (Box 15)
  - 1991 (Box 15)
  - Marshall Retirement Clippings, 1991 (Box 15)
  - Marshall Obituaries, 1992 (Box 15)
- Planners
  - 1955-1971 (Box 16)
  - 1973-1978 (Box 17)
  - 1979-1984 (Box 18)
  - 1985-1988 (Box 19)
  - 1989-1992 (Box 20)